Guide to the James Robinson Smith Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
James Robinson Smith papers
1888-1964
MS 1634
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
The papers consist of correspondence and subject files primarily documenting the personal life of James Robinson Smith. Several of the subject files document his scholarship, personal beliefs, and work with the Red Cross and food rationing.
Smith, Robinson, 1876-1954
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lucinda Smith King, 1992.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Correspondence, 1888-1964. II. Subject Files, 1898-1954.
Biographical / Historical
James Robinson Smith was born in Hartford, Connecticut on December 27, 1876. He graduated from Yale College in 1898 and did graduate work at Yale and Harvard, receiving his M.A. from Yale in 1904. After graduating, he traveled, worked at a variety of jobs, and engaged in literary pursuits. A writer and scholar, he translated Don Quixote and The Earliest Lives of Dante, did scholarly work on Homer's Iliad and the Bible, and published lists of famous men and great quotations. He also wrote poetry. In World War I, Smith worked on and wrote pamphlets about food rationing in European nations, particularly Belgium. After the war he worked in Europe with the American Red Cross. He spent most of the remainder of his life in Nice, France, writing and working at the English-American Library. In 1905 Smith married Martha Butler, who died in 1910. Their daughter, Lucinda, was born in 1909. Smith died in Nice on June 12, 1954.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence and subject files primarily documenting the personal life of James Robinson Smith. Several of the subject files document his scholarship, personal beliefs, and work with the Red Cross and food rationing.
Smith, Robinson, 1876-1954; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1898
- Correspondence, 1888-1964; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series is arranged in two sections: James Robinson Smith and Lucinda Smith. The James Robinson Smith correspondence comprises non-family and family, incoming and outgoing letters, arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent. The Lucinda Smith correspondence comprises incoming letters from family members and one folder of letters of condolences she received upon her father's death.
  - Smith, James Robinson
    - Non-family
      - Incoming
        - Chilton, Carroll Brent, 1923-1924, 1930-1933, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Cook, Albert S., 1912, 1918-1924, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
        - Crane, William, 1922, 1925, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
        - de Selincourt, Basil, 1918, 1923-1931, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - Fahnstock, Wallace, 1912-1913, 1922-1924, 1934, 1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - Goodwin, Harriet, 1896, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
        - Gregg, Margaret, 1914, 1923-1934, 1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
        - Hapgood, Melvin and Mary, 1897-1899 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Hattersly, Isabelle, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        - Hooker, E. B., 1895 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        - Means, Stuart, 1913, 1919-1925, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
        - Montgomery, Francis, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
        - Moon, Dabney, 1922-1925 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        - Osgood, Charles, 1923, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        - Phelps, William Lyon, 1912, 1922,-1924, 1932, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
        - Prentiss, Janet, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
        - Robinson, Charles M., 1893-1898, undated (Box 1, Folder 17 - 20)
        - Sedgwick, Alice, 1912, 1920-1926, undated (Box 1, Folder 21 - 22)
        - Smith, Nancy, 1920-1926, 1951, 1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
        - Stanton, Stephen B., 1890-1893, 1895-1898, undated (Box 1, Folder 24 - 25)
        - Torrey, Charles C., 1950, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
        - Wilson, Ellen, 1895-1898 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Outgoing
        - Chilton, Carroll Brent, 1924, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 28)
        - Cook, Albert S., 1922-1924 (Box 2, Folder 29)
        - Crane, William, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 30)
        - De Selincourt, Basil, 1910, 1933, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
        - Fahnestock, Wallace, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 32)
        - Giles, May, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 33)
        - Gregg, Margaret, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 34)
        - Howley, Roswell, 1931, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 35)
        - Imbria, Robert, 1923, 1924, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
        - Moody, Harriet, 1919-1929, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
        - Moon, Dabney, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 38)
        - Phelps, William Lyon, 1912, 1924-1926, 1939, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
        - Prentiss, Janet, 1924, 1925, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
        - Sartorio, Rev., 1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
        - Smith, Nancy, 1923-1940 (Box 2, Folder 42)
        - Spalding, Alexandrine, 1923, 1924, 1931, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
        - Stanton, Stephen B., 1925, 1931-1939, 1944, 1949-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Family
      - Incoming
        - General, 1897 (Box 3, Folder 45)
        - Butler, Grandmama [Florence], 1913, 1922-1924 (Box 3, Folder 46)
        - Hapgood, Dorothy, 1923, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
        - Smith, Annie, 1913, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
        - Smith, Douglas, 1913, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 49)
        - Smith, Goodwin, 1922-1925, 1932, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 50)
        - Smith, Helen Tracy, 1915, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
        - Smith, James A. [father], 1888-1898 (Box 3, Folder 52)
        - Smith, Lucinda, 1933, 1945, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
        - Smith, Mary Ann [aunt], 1898 (Box 3, Folder 54)
        - Smith, Mary Morgan [grandmother], Undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
        - Smith, Max, 1924-1925, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
        - Taylor, Bertha, 1912-1913, 1925, undated (Box 3, Folder 57)
        - Tracy, Mary, 1923-1924 (Box 3, Folder 58)
      - Outgoing
        - General, 1911, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 59)
        - Aunt Ella [Ayres], 1913 (Box 3, Folder 60)
        - Butler, Grandmama [Florence], 1911-1933, undated (Box 3, Folder 61 - 66)
        - Hapgood, Dorothy [and Lucinda Smith], 1947, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 67)
        - Hapgood, Mary, 1925-1928, 1944-1949 (Box 3, Folder 68)
        - Pease, Alice, 1924-1925, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 69)
        - Sister [letters addressed to "Dear Sister"], 1942-1945 (Box 3, Folder 70)
        - Smith, Douglas Tracy, 1911-1917, 1930-1934 (Box 3, Folder 71)
        - Smith, Goodwin, 1924-1937, 1946-1952, undated (Box 3, Folder 72)
        - Smith, Lucinda [daughter]
          - 1917-1934, undated (Box 4, Folder 73 - 80)
          - 1935-1953, undated (Box 5, Folder 81 - 86)
        - Taylor, Bertha, 1916, 1923, 1925 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Lucinda Smith
    - Family [Ayres, Taylor, Hapgood, Butler], 1927-1947, undated (Box 5, Folder 88 - 90)
    - Condolences [re: death of James Robinson Smith], 1954-1955, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 91)
- Subject Files, 1898-1954; Series II
  The files contain correspondence, publications, and miscellaneous items relating to the professional occupations and personal interests of James Robinson Smith. The series is arranged in alphabetical order by subject.
  - ABC's of living [practical rules for life], 1917-1919 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Addresses, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Beautiful buildings [lists of photographs of], Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Belgium [involvement with Commission for Relief in Belgium, 1917-1919], 1914-1919, 1925, 1954, undated (Box 6, Folder 4 - 7)
  - Beliefs [correspondence with philosophical content], 1924, 1939, 1946, 1951, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Children's Bible, 1923, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Children's library, 1922, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Don Quixote, 1910-1932 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Education [letter regarding education in Europe], 1921? (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Famous men [correspondence and his published list of famous men], 1898, 1939-1942, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Famous quotations, 1924, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Father [typical letter to Lucinda], 1938, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Finances, 1925, 1942, 1953, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Florida, 1943-1945 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - France, Undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Hartford, Undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Homeopathy [rules for healthy living], 1944, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Homeric studies [sources of Iliad ], 1923-1926, 1930, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Hoover, Herbert [correspondence, description], 1928, 1952, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Italian renaissance, Undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Italy trip, 1922 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Latvia, Finland, Russia [Red Cross work], 1919-1920 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Lay reader [church-related materials], 1924-1925, 1948-1949, 1954, undated (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Library systems, 1951, undated (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Newspapers [articles about James Robinson Smith], 1931, 1940-1941, undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Nice library, 1924, 1938, undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Paintings, 1938, undated (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Peace [international affairs, interwar period], 1931, undated (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Percenter [rules for gambling], 1937-1941, 1944, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Permit (residence), 1951 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Pioneers of Science [letter about book by that title], 1947 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Poetry selections [from others' poetry], 1913, 1934, undated (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Poultry, 1911, undated (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Prayer, 1932, undated (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Publishers, 1898, 1923, undated (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Scotland Yard, 1919, 1927, 1929-1930, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Sons of the American Revolution, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Spain [pamphlets, correspondence], 1914, 1926, undated (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Spanish mystics, 1926 (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Stamps, 1924-1925, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Street girls [social and charitable activities on behalf of], 1917, 1931, undated (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Synoptic problem [New Testament scholarship], 1911-1912, 1921, 1923, 1945, undated (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Wars
    - Pre-WWI, 1912-1913, undated (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - WWI, 1914-1918 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Pre-WWII, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - WWII, 1939-1940, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Yale [correspondence, class-related material], 1897-1898, 1923, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 51)